查克的一生
蒙太奇字幕组 原创翻译 转载须遵循CC BY-NC-SA 4.0协议
翻译：小P  后期：novaeye & 小P
字幕组纳新TG：MontageSubs
第三幕
谢谢你 查克
课后兴趣班纳新
游泳社团
舞蹈社团
数学竞赛社
课后兴趣班纳新
游泳社团
舞蹈社团
数学竞赛社
游泳社团
舞蹈社团
数学竞赛社
...这非混沌 也非死亡
"It is not chaos or death.
是形象 契合 蓝图
"It is form and union and plan.
是永恒的生命
"It is eternal life.
是幸福
"It is happiness.
过去与现在都已凋零
"The past and present wilt.
诗为美国诗人沃尔特·惠特曼《草叶集·自我之歌》
我充盈它们 又将它们掏空
"I have filled them, emptied them,
然后继续去充盈未来的下一折页
"and proceed to fill my next fold of the future.
云端的倾听者啊！有何秘密要向我倾诉？
"Listener up there! What have you to confide to me?
当我细嗅暮色时 直视我的面庞
"Look in my face while I snuff the sidle of evening.
放心说吧 无人能闻得见 我只多留片刻
"Talk honestly, no one else hears you, and I stay only a minute longer."
我是否自相矛盾？
"Do I contradict myself?
好吧 那我就自相矛盾
"Very well then, I contradict myself.
我心疆无限 我包罗万象
I am large, I contain multitudes."
天哪
My God.
怎么了？
What is it?
什么事让你打断惠特曼的诗？
Clearly something more interesting than Whitman.
是加州 那又地震了
California. There was another earthquake.
从圣巴巴拉到弗雷斯诺一大片地都没了...
A huge chunk's gone from Santa Barbara to Fresno.
-太可怕了 -...沉入大海了
-It's fucking crazy. -Into the ocean.
-就那样没了 -别慌 别慌
-Just like that. -Alright, alright.
"全  没  了!"
9.1级地震袭击加州
冷静
Settle down.
无网络连接
没网了
Got no connection.
你们有网吗？
Anybody else have one?
没有
No.
抱歉 网还用不了
Oh, eh, sorry. Network's still down.
无网络连接
不过 这有纸质文件
I've got his file here, though.
迪伦最近在摸鱼
Uh, Dylan's been diving lately.
这学期他成绩从A和B跌到了D
I mean, this semester, he's gone from As and Bs to Ds.
你有纸质备份？
You keep hard copies?
当网时好时坏时就开始保存了
When the network started acting up, a lot of us started keeping hard copies.
你觉得这次网还能恢复吗？
What do you think? I mean, you think it's coming back?
我不知道
Well, I don't, I don't know.
我还记得互联网诞生前的世界
I remember the world before the internet.
没网的惨状不难想象
Why is it so hard to imagine carrying on without it?
对吧？
It is, though, isn't it?
还能恢复网吗？还有戏吗？
How do we go back? How... Can we go back?
如果这次彻底没戏了怎么活？
What if it's down for good this time?
还没网
Internet's still down.
是没网 但别担心
Yeah, but lucky for us,
我有所有学生的纸质文件
I've got hard copies for each student.
我有预感
I think this might be it.
我感觉这次网不会恢复了
I don't think it's coming back this time.
你八成是对的
You might be right.
但重点是艾米丽 她开始旷课了
But I do think we should talk about Emily.  Her attendance has really fallen off.
她旷课了？
Her attendance?
全球旷工旷课都破天荒了
Absenteeism's at an all-time high all over the world.
医生旷 飞行员旷 警察也旷
We got doctors and pilots and cops
大家都他妈擅离职守
and everyone's just pissing the fuck off, right?
但你却只想着艾米丽？
But you, you want to talk to us about Emily?
现在还怎么上课？
How are they supposed to study, anyway?
网络崩溃已经八个月了
Web's been on the fritz for eight months.
有一半网站都是乱码
Half those sites are just garbled.
我懂 网坏了
I mean, I get it, sites go dark.
但其他问题呢？
But what about all that other stuff?
有些网站还好
Like, sites are there,
但都是错字和错误标点
but all the punctuation's wrong. words spelled wrong.
你能解释吗？
How do you explain that?
我不能
Well, I can't,
但布莱恩还能来上课
but Brian can still prepare for class.
即便没网 课本都还在啊
I mean, the library's still here. Internet or not.
色情网站没了
Pornhub's down.
安德森老师 你知道吗？
Did you know that, Mr. Anderson?
呃 是啊
Yeah, I, uh,
我 我 我听说了 是的
I, I, I had noticed that. Yeah.
对不起 布瑞给你添麻烦了
Sorry if Bri's been any trouble.
这家就我一人了
It's just me now.
他妈妈跑了 我不知道去哪了
His mom... she left, I don't know where.
听说最近这事常见
That's been happening a lot more I hear,
人们只是玩失踪
people just ghosting.
她高中那会儿认识个无缘的男友
Hers was some star-crossed boyfriend from high school.
待在一起有一个月吧
They dated a month.
那该死的一个月
Goddamn month.
就为了那一个月 她竟然丢下二十年的感情
She's gonna throw 20 years in the trash to chase down a month.
我猜她一直藕断丝连他
I guess she never stopped thinking about him.
谁心里没有放不下的人
I guess we've all got someone like that.
我懂 我懂
I mean, I get it,
就像那些穿紫袍说的那样 要真是末日了
if it really is the end, like those kooks in the purple robes say,
最终和谁一起面对呢？
then who do you want to be with for it?
她要抛弃骨肉吗？
But to leave her son?
对了 她说会回来的
Uh, she says she'll be back.
我也不确定
I don't know. Um...
该死的色情网站
Fuckin' Pornhub.
万一永远不回来了呢？
What if that never comes back?
真他妈的倒霉
Fuckin' tragedy.
就算这真是一切的结局
I mean, even if it is the end of all things...
这也提前把我结束了
that's just fuckin' mean.
-见笑了 -嗯
-Sorry. -Yeah.
美国新闻 北加州变成废墟
北加州满目疮痍 令人心碎
It's a scene of devastation and heartbreak in California,
救援人员正努力在残骸中搜寻
as rescue workers sift through what remains of the northern portion of the state.
造成北约克郡350人死亡
350 dead in North Yorkshire
英国新闻 约克郡惨剧
水位还在持续上涨...
as water levels continue to...
法国新闻 巨大海啸袭击布列塔尼海岸
(法语) 高达八十米巨浪袭击朱门灯塔
墨西哥新闻 蒙特雷被森林大火吞噬
(西班牙语) 大规模疏散以应对这种前所未有的...
德国新闻 韦尔辛根火山喷发
(德语) 岩浆正在流向韦尔辛根
日本新闻 警察与抗议者发生冲突
(日语) 示威者在...
意大利新闻 灾难性洪水吞噬利沃诺住宅
(意大利语) 洪水淹没了整个...
马蒂·安德森第一次看到那广告牌那天
The day Marty Anderson first saw the billboard
恰巧就在互联网彻底瘫痪前
was just before the internet finally went down for good.
在那之前网时好时坏有八个月了
It had been wobbling for eight months,
但占据头条的是其他事件
but other problems, like fires, earthquakes,
像是大火 地震 鸟和鱼的彻底灭绝
and whole species of birds and fish dying off had taken priority.
...烧到现在 这成为美国史上最严重的山火
...till today, thought to be the largest wildfire in United States history.
在过去 马蒂会直接走收费公路
Ordinarily, Marty would've driven by way of the Turnpike bypass,
但自奥特溪桥塌了后那条路就走不通了
but that wasn't possible due to the collapse of the bridge over Otter Creek.
查尔斯·查克·克兰兹
39个非凡岁月！
谢谢你
查克！
查尔斯·查克·克兰兹
39个非凡岁月！
谢谢你
查克！
由于加州最近的灾难
Well, with what happened in California,
内华达州现在是全美人口最多的州
that officially makes Nevada one of the most populous states in the Union now.
但需要强调的是...
The thing that must be said here is...
菲莉西娅·戈登是市立医院的护士
Felicia Gordon is a nurse at City General.
最近几周她却更像是名收殓员
Though for the last few weeks, she's felt more like an undertaker.
自夏末以来员工就不断的辞职
The staff, whose numbers have been dwindling since late summer,
大家给自己起名叫“自杀小队”
have begun referring to themselves as the Suicide Squad.
稍事休息
We'll be back to talk more about this
稍后将带来中西部大火和缺水的最新情况
and, uh, also about the fires in the Midwest, speaking of water scarcity, back after this break.
感谢查尔斯·查克·克兰兹39年来的非凡岁月
We'd like to say thank you to Charles Krantz for 39 great years.
谢谢你 查克
Thanks, Chuck.
嘿
Hey.
听说你又救了一个？
Heard you got another one.
嗯 又一个
Yeah. One more.
我的没那么幸运 手腕都割烂了 你懂的
Mine wasn't so lucky. Slit wrists, so...
真没办法了
what were we supposed to do really?
听说玛丽露的事了吗？
Hear about Marilou?
没 怎么了？
No. What about Marilou?
她不干了
She left!
-还记得她前任佩德罗吗？ -记得
-Her ex. Remember Pedro? -Mm-hm.
他冒出来 嘟囔了几句
He showed up, and I don't know what he said to her,
两人牵着手就走了
but she walked out holding his hand.
他们离婚离的有多难熬
And I remember how bad that divorce was.
-有印象吗？ -嗯 记得
-Do you remember? -Yeah, I remember.
好吧 往事如烟了 他们又拉上了手
Well, I guess that's all bridge water 'cause off she went.
...地陷不断出现
...sinkholes that have been opening up.
现在婚姻都咋样？
I wonder what the stats are.
是分居多还是复合多？
You think more people are splitting up or getting back together?
是结婚多还是离婚多？
I mean, do you think marriage rates are up or divorce rates...
结婚多
Marriages.
-你是个乐天派 -不
-You're an optimist. -No.
离婚周期长 没人会去排这个队
Divorce takes way longer, and I don't think anyone's filing.
填文件就得半年多 何苦呢？
Why bother? Six months of paperwork at least. Probably more.
结婚领证上下只要一小时
Marriage license is one page and it takes an hour or so.
所以我猜结婚多
I'm gonna guess marriages.
午餐不见你 晚餐也不在
Missed you for lunch, missed you for dinner.
电影《封面女郎》(1944)
怎么了？辟谷了吗？
What's the matter? Don't you eat anymore?
好吧 我不饿
Well, I wasn't hungry tonight.
那你今早也不饿吗？
Weren't you hungry this morning either?
谁拿了我的舞蹈袜？天哪 谁那么坏
Who stole my nylons? Egads! The very...
菲莉西娅·戈登来电
不饿
Not very.
昨晚排练到很晚吗？
Too much rehearsal last night, huh?
就像锻炼一样
It was kind of a workout.
赖床了？所以今早来的那么晚
That why you slept late?
我可没晚起
Oh, I didn't sleep late.
我去了富人区
I went uptown.
-去购物？ -不是
-Shopping? -No.
喂
Hey.
Hi.
你给挂了？
You hung up?
是啊
Yeah.
但后来想你看的到 所以又...
But then I figured you probably saw it. So...
还好吗？
How are you?
还行吧
I'm okay, I guess.
你呢？
How are you?
我上班时想到你了
I was, um, thinking about you today.
当时在猜结婚多还是离婚多
We were at work talking about marriages and divorces. Like, which are happening more now...
我赌结婚多
Marriages, I bet.
没人愿意等离婚
Ain't nobody waiting on a divorce.
那么再婚呢？
What about remarriages?
要约炮得先请我喝酒
You want to buy a guy a drink first or...
我打赌人们都在再复合
I bet those are happening.
这很有意义
I mean, it makes sense.
人们现在渴望慰藉和熟悉的事物
People wanting something comforting and familiar.
那么 你今天过得怎么样？
So... how was your day?
你想复合的意图太明显了 不觉得吗？
You're just going right for it, aren't you?
陪我聊聊
Humor me.
呃 今天就那样
It was, um...It was a day, I guess.
有点怪
You know? Weird.
家长会开的就像对牛弹琴
Parent-teacher sessions, felt like pissing in the wind.
你听说加州的事儿了吧？
You know about California, right?
听说了
Yeah.
我听说大部分人都迁移了
I know they're saying most of it was already evacuated,
今天就有几十万灾民东迁
but I heard today there are hundreds of thousands of refugees trekking east.
知道现在内华达州是全美人口最多的州吗？
Did you know Nevada is one of the most  populous states in the Union now?
听国家电台科学家说 加州就跟烂墙皮一样往下掉
I heard a, a scientist on NPR say California is peeling away like old wallpaper.
今天下午 日本又有一座核电站被淹
And another Japanese reactor got inundated this afternoon.
他们虽说 停机了 一切安全
And they're saying, you know, it was shut down and all's well,
但我就是没法相信
but I just, I, I don't think I believe that.
你真是个怀疑论者
Cynic.
好吧 马蒂 这日子就是这么不靠谱
Well, we're living in cynical times, Marty.
不少人都认为天要塌了
I mean, some people think we're living in the last times.
不再是邪教成员这样想了
Not just the religious crazies either. Not anymore.
市立医院自杀小队的许多专家也这样说
And you are hearing that from a member in good standing of the City General Suicide Squad.
那是我们的自称
That's what we call ourselves now.
可没瞎说
No lie.
今天有6人没挺过来 但救回了18人 主要用纳洛酮
We lost six today, but there's 18 more we dragged back, mostly with naloxone.
但这种药已经供不上了
But supplies of that are getting very thin.
我听药房说最多坚持到月底
And I heard the head pharmacist say we might be completely out by the end of the month.
太倒霉了
That sucks.
是啊 是啊
Yeah. Yeah.
是的 太倒霉了 真的太倒霉了
Yeah, that sucks. It, it really sucks.
互联网瘫痪 加州下沉
The internet's down, and California's hanging by a thread.
还有大火 饥荒 疫情和各种灾难
There's fires and famines and plagues and all the rest.
连我们医院也快崩溃了
I mean, it just the center doesn't hold.
没完没了
It just won't let up.
那天还有多久？
How long is this gonna go on?
那之前还能撑多久？
How much can we take before the whole thing...
我是说 天塌下来前
before the whole thing goes apart, I mean.
卡尔·萨根是知名的美国天文学家
我在教孩子们 卡尔·萨根 的理论
I'm teaching the kids Carl Sagan right now.
你听说过他的宇宙历年法吗？
You ever hear what he said about the cosmic calendar?
呃 想不起来 应该没听过
Uh... I don't know. I don't think so.
你知道 宇宙已有150亿年历史
Well, the universe is 15 billion years old.
如果你把这150亿年
And if you took all of that all, all 15 billion years
都给它压缩到365天的日历中
and compress them into a single calendar year,
那么宇宙大爆炸发生在1月1日第一秒
then the Big Bang happens in the first second, January 1st.
一    月    份
而如今
And, and today,
我们正处于12月31日 最后一天的最后一刻
oh, right now, we're in the final millisecond of the last minute of the last day, December 31st.
十 二 月 份
回到起点
But if you go back to the start,
回到大爆炸发生的1月1日夜里
if the, if the Big Bang happens at midnight, January 1st,
日历里每个月等于12.5亿年
then each month of this calendar is one and a quarter billion years long.
嘿 别考我数学
Hey, nobody told me there was math on this exam.
宇宙在1月1日诞生
The universe starts January 1st,
但此时我们的银河系还没形成 形成要到5月
but the, uh, the Milky Way didn't form until May.
五月份
我们的太阳和地球 要到9月中旬才形成
Our sun and our earth, they don't show up until mid-September.
九   月   份
生命不久后就有了 但没轮到我们
Life appears soon after. But not us.
猜猜我们什么时候出现的？
No. No, no, we don't appear for guess how long?
再说一遍 今天不考数学
Again, I was told there'd be no math.
在12月31日
December 31st.
出现在日历上的最后一天
Last day on the calendar,
十 二 月 份
最早的人类出现在晚上10点半左右
and the very first human beings on Earth made their debut around 10:30 p.m.
出现在最后一天的晚上10点半
10:30 p.m. on the last day.
每一分钟代表着3万年
And, um, every minute since then is 30,000 years.
晚上11:46 距离午夜14分钟 人类才学会用火
So, 11:46 p.m., only 14 minutes ago, humanity tamed fire
在距离午夜只剩几秒钟时
and now we're out of minutes, we're into seconds.
到11点59分20秒
11:59 and 20 seconds,
动植物才被驯化 人类刚开始能制造工具
the domestication of plants and animals begin, an application for the human talent for making tools.
到11点59分35秒
11:59 and 35 seconds,
农耕社区演变为首批城市雏形
agricultural communities evolved into the first cities.
我们记载的所有历史
Our recorded history,
听说过的所有人
everyone we've ever heard of,
所有历史书上的事 都只发生在最后10秒钟里
every single thing in any one of our history books happens in the last 10 seconds.
所有事都集中在最后一天最后一分钟的最后十秒
The last 10 seconds of the last minute of the last day on the calendar.
日历的最后一天
December 31st.
该怎么回答你那天还有多久？
So how long is it gonna go on?
我不知道 小菲
I don't know, Fel.
要是你说得对 很可能真是这样
If you're right, and you might be,
这可能就是末世 宇宙正在消亡
that this really is the, the last times and the universe is dying,
就算它在快速消亡
and let's just say it's a fast death,
即使这一切都发生在最后一秒
even if all of this is happening in the, the last split second,
最后一微秒
microsecond,
谁知道对我们来说是多久
who knows how long that'll last.
也许是几秒钟 也可以是无限长
Maybe seconds, maybe eons.
也许发生在宇宙吐出最后一口气的时候
Maybe all this is happening as the cosmos burps out its last breath.
也许发生在宇宙最后一次心跳的时候
Maybe it's all happening in the last single solitary heartbeat.
你真能说 马蒂
Jesus, Marty.
是吧
Yeah.
好了 小菲 我该挂了 我...
Listen, Fel, I should go. I've, um...
还得批改试卷呢
I've got tests to grade.
马蒂
Marty...
一切都完了 我们也只剩下句真倒霉
the world is going down the drain, and all we can say is, "That sucks."
说不定谁都躲不掉这劫
So, maybe we're going down the drain too.
说不定
Maybe.
听说了吗 查克·克兰兹要退休了
But, you know, Chuck Krantz is retiring.
都要天塌下来了 还有这个插曲
So...I guess there's a gleam of light in the darkness.
听说了 39个非凡岁月
Yes. Thirty-nine great years.
哦 你也看到那个奇葩的广告牌了？
Oh, you saw that weird billboard?
不 是从收音机里听到的广告
No, it was an ad on the radio that, um,
之前跟你讲的那个国家电台
that NPR show I was telling you about.
国资电台都开始打广告了 这真是世界末日了
If they're running ads on NPR, it really is the end of the world.
查克·克兰兹会怎么计算广告覆盖率
Tell me, how does Chuck Krantz rate this kind of coverage?
我是说 他像个会计师
I mean... looks like an accountant.
我从没听说过他
I've never heard of him.
广告一定用了张老照片
Used an old photo too, I guess.
他看着都不到40 咋来的40年工龄
I mean, the guy barely looks 40 at all, let alone 40 years on the job.
无奇不有
The world is full of mysteries.
嘿 马蒂 别喝烈酒了
And, hey, no hard stuff, Marty.
喝点啤酒吧
Okay? Have a beer instead.
遵命
You got it.
俄州环保局对克利夫兰一带下达了空气红色警报
The Ohio EPA has now issued a code red air quality alert for Cleveland and its surrounding...
俄州山火蔓延 克利夫兰居民紧急疏散
（滚动新闻：余震后加州海岸线不断下沉）
电影《封面女郎》(1944)
信号中断
我勒个去
Shit on a stick.
感谢查尔斯·查克·克兰兹39年来的非凡岁月
We'd like to say thank you to Charles Krantz for 39 great years.
查尔斯·查克·克兰兹
谢谢你 查克
Thanks, Chuck.
查尔斯·查克·克兰兹
39个非凡岁月！
谢谢你
查克！
信号中断
格斯
Gus!
哦 嘿 马蒂
Oh. Hey, Marty.
怎么不开车了？
Where's your car?
车 车停在半山腰了 好几百辆车都扔路上了
It's... it's on, it's on the sidewalk halfway down Main Street Hill with a hundred others.
我只好步行
I finally just had to turn around.
该死 我走了
Fuck it, I walked...
猜我走了多远？ 这有五公里了吧？
What do you think it is, like, three miles?
我走了将近五公里
I just walked three miles.
哦 你是这要去学校吧 等下
Oh, you're going to school. Hold on a sec.
呃 我想下 你得绕 你得绕
Uh, real quick, you gotta, you gotta go,
你得绕道走11号公路
listen to me, you gotta go out Route 11
然后在转到19号公路
and then hook back on, on, on 19.
是呀 路上会很堵
Yeah. There's gonna be plenty of traffic.
你大概得绕至少30公里
You gotta go out at least 20 miles.
运气好中午能到
You might make it before lunch.
-别指望早到 -发生了什么事？
-I wouldn't count on it. -What happened?
市场街和主街交叉那有大地坑
Giant sinkhole opened up on Market and Main.
老兄 陷得太大了
Man, the-the thing, it, uh, it's huge.
要么是降雨导致的
All the rain probably had something to do with it,
要么是缺乏维护
lack of maintenance maybe more so.
至少轮不到我去修
But it's not my department, thank God.
但是 坑下面得有二十多辆车吧
But, yeah, there's, there's gotta be 20 cars at the bottom.
那些车里的人 永远上不来了
And some of the people in some of those cars, they ain't comin' back.
老天 我昨天下班就堵在那里
Jesus, I was, I was just there last night,
堵在那好久
backed up in traffic.
幸好你今早不在那里
Thank God you weren't there this morning.
听说加州的事了吧
I assume you know about California.
我今早没看电视
I didn't turn on the TV this morning.
-难怪 -有什么新闻吗？
-Oh! -Is there something new?
都沉下去了
The, the rest of it went.
电视说北加州20%还尚存
I-I mean, th-they're saying that 20% of Northern California is hanging in there,
实际也许还剩10%
which probably means, what, 10%?
但是粮食产区都没了
But the food-producing regions are... they're gone.
中西部被烧成个焦土
And with the Midwest turning to charcoal
佛州又被水淹
and Florida flooding, that's like
全国粮仓都没了
all the food-producing regions in the country just gone.
欧洲的情况也差不多
And the same thing with Europe.
亚洲也在闹饥荒
I mean, it's famine time in Asia.
听说那死了一百万人
There's a million people dead.
他们管它叫做 树...树疫
They're saying it's the bub-bublonic,
-树疫病 -鼠疫
-bubonic plague. -Bubonic.
对 鼠...鼠疫
Bu-Bubonic plague. Yeah.
还有蜜蜂 十多年前就不正常
And the bees, I mean, they were in trouble a decade ago,
但现在所有蜜蜂都没了
but they're completely gone now.
也许南美洲还有几个蜂巢吧
I mean, there's a couple of hives or whatever down in South America,
但不产蜂蜜
but there ain't no honey, honey.
没有这些小虫虫 怎么给剩下的庄稼授粉呢
And without those little guys, like, what's gonna pollinate all the crops we have left?
要我说 我可...
I mean, I can't do...
先打住 稍后聊
Excuse me. One sec.
哦 哦 好
Yeah, yeah. That's-that's cool.
是 安 安德莉娅吗？
A-Andrea? Are you,
你是中西部信托银行的安德莉娅吗？
are you Andrea from Midwest Trust?
我是菲莉西娅·安德森的丈夫
I'm Felicia Anderson's husband.
实际上 是前夫
Ex, actually.
我觉得你和小菲互相认识
I think you and Fel know each other.
我们之前在大卫家聚会时见过
We met at a, a, a game night at David's.
几晚游戏聚会
A few game nights.
对 记得
Yeah, sure.
你想干什么？
What do you want?
车堵在路上 我刚走了半天
I just had a long walk, and my car is stuck,
而银行 斜了
and the bank is, it's leaning.
斜了？
Leaning?
是的
Yeah.
银行就在地坑旁边
It's on the edge of the sinkhole.
估计我的职业生涯到此为止
Guess that's the end of my job.
嘿 你们银行上头那广告牌是啥意思
Hey, I'm curious about the billboard on the bank building.
-你看到了吗？ -怎么能躲得过？
-Have you seen it? -How could I miss it?
那广告还出现在电视上
And I saw the ads too, on TV.
电视不再播卖车卖家具的广告了
No more ads for cars or discount furniture.
只播“感谢查尔斯·克兰兹39年来的非凡岁月 谢谢你 查克”
Just, "Charles Krantz, 39 great years. Thanks, Chuck."
他不是你银行的人？
So, he doesn't work at the bank?
他不是从你银行退休？
He's not retiring from the bank?
我根本不认识这个人
I don't know Charles Krantz.
我觉得这就是个恶搞 玩行为艺术
I think it's just a prank. Performance art.
你保重
Take care.
他们看起来像是灾民
They look like refugees.
是啊
Yeah.
至少大家不再惊慌失措了
No one looks that concerned.
那又怎样？
What good would that do?
刚开始大家都惊慌失措
All was concerned at the start.
还记得那些抗议吗？
Remember the protests?
还记得他们推倒白宫的围栏吗？
You remember they knocked over the fence at the White House,
记得他们向那些学生开枪吗？
and all those students got shot?
-是的 -还有俄罗斯政府被推翻
-Yeah. -And the overthrow of the Russian government.
巴基斯坦和印度间的四日战争
You got the Four Day War between Pakistan and India
还有他妈的德国火山喷发
and the fucking... the volcano in Germany.
德国火山还能喷发 太扯了
There was a volcano in Germany. That's, that's crazy.
我们自我安慰“一切都会过去的”
And we just kept saying, "Oh, it's gonna blow over."
看来过不去的 对吧？
That doesn't look to be happening, though, does it?
是啊
No.
我觉得自杀的人最终会减少
I think that suicides will slow down.
我觉得人们最终会等待
I think people will just...wait.
等什么？
For what?
等结局
The end.
万物的大结局
This is the end of everything.
库伯勒-罗丝悲伤模型五阶段：否认 愤怒 恳求 沮丧 接受
我们正处在 悲伤模型 第五阶段
I mean, we're, we're going through the five stages of grief.
你明白吗？咱们到了最后阶段
Don't you get it? I mean, we just, we just landed on the final stage.
接受
Acceptance.
等待 才是最难熬的
The waiting...I think that's the hardest part.
灾难不打声招呼就冒出来了
And the whole thing, it just, it-it came out of nowhere, right?
我是说 大家早知道有自然环境问题
I mean, everyone knew there was trouble with the environment.
即便是右翼疯子也私下里心知肚明
I mean, I think even the right-wing nutjobs were secretly, they got it.
但现在
But this...
现在这些
this...
现在这些不过是各种屁事的集合
this is just 60 different varieties of shit.
屁事来的太快了
It's just so much shit that happened fast.
现在一年都十四个月了
It's like a year, man. Fourteen months.
倒霉啊
Sucks.
是啊 倒霉啊
Yeah. Sucks.
飞机写字
Skywriting.
长大后就再也没见过这种事
I haven't seen one of those since I was a kid.
谢谢你 亠亠
搞什么鬼？
What the fuck?
我也想问同样的问题
My sentiments... exactly.
谢谢你 查克
谢谢你 查克！
街头艺人万岁
查克万岁
查克我爱你
查克yyds
爱你 查克
喂 喂 喂  你上哪去了？
Whoa, whoa, whoa, where have you been?
你不知道吗？我跑过来的
Are you kidding? I had to run here.
路全堵了 一半人把车都仍路上了
The traffic's insane, and half the cars are empty.
温斯顿医生跑了
Dr. Winston's MIA.
-什么意思？ -你没听错
-What? -Yeah.
他今天早上过来看了一圈转头就走了
He walked in this morning, and he looked around and he walked out again.
再也找不到他了
And now I can't find him.
他把对讲机都扔门口了
He dropped his pager when he walked out.
好 那我来开刀
Okay. I'll scrub in.
床位都空了
The beds are empty.
病人基本都自己走出去了 我把最后一个扶出去的
Most of them walked out. I-I-I transferred the last of the stable ones.
但是 菲莉西娅 有点怪事
But, Felicia, there's something weird.
怎么回事？
What is that?
机子坏了吗？
What's wrong with the monitor?
这就是怪事 不只这一台
That's the thing, it-it's, it's not just that one.
我搞不懂 小菲 搞不懂
I don't know, Fel. I don't know.
我 我也不想待在这了
I mean... I might want to get out of here.
我想回家
I might wanna go home.
没必要再待在这了
I don't think I need to be here anymore.
信号中断
菲莉西娅
呼出失败 无信号
查尔斯·查克·克兰兹
39个非凡岁月！
谢谢你
查克！
还好吗 老先生？
You okay, sir?
好 就歇歇脚
Yeah. Just taking a rest.
我走去市中心看大地坑了
I walked downtown to look at the sinkhole
还用手机拍了几张照片
and take a few pictures with my phone.
我以为电视台可能会想要
Thought one of the local TV stations might be interested,
但全都停播了
but they all seem to be off the air.
除了克兰兹的广告
Except for pictures of Krantz.
到处都是克兰兹啊
All Krantz all the time.
-知道他是谁吗？ -不知道
-Any idea who he is? -None.
我问过至少二十多人 没人知道
I've asked two dozen people, at least. Nobody knows.
我们的克兰兹可是世界末日的领路人啊
Our man, Krantz, is the Oz of the apocalypse.
最后的笑话
Our last meme.
-你往哪走？ -丰收里
-Where are you heading? -Harvest Acres.
世外桃源般的小区
Nice little enclave off the beaten track.
我正要去那儿
I'm heading there myself.
-我前妻住那儿 -噢
-My ex lives there. -Huh.
好吧
Well...
要一起去吗？
I can walk with you if you like.
萨姆 你做什么工作的？
What do you do, Sam?
如果还有工作的话
If you still do anything, I mean.
亚伯勒殡仪馆的老板兼首席殡葬师
Owner and chief undertaker for Yarborough Funeral Home.
噢 老天
Oh, man!
是啊
Yeah.
生意之前好到爆
We had a boom.
谈起这个就高兴
It's hard to feel good about it,
最火的还是前几周
but business was never better than it was a few weeks ago.
但我真正志向所在是气象学
But my real interest's meteorology.
年轻时我曾想当电视上天气预报员
Dreamed of being a television weatherman in my salad days,
也许能成全国台的
maybe even one of the networks.
但 没成
But n-no.
不过还继续关注着
I keep up, though.
读有关的书
Read the journals.
想听的话 有些我读到的奇闻异事
And I can tell you something amazing if you want to hear.
大家都说一天有24小时 对吧？
You know how people say there are 24 hours in a day?
其实他们错了
Well, they're wrong.
在恒星日中一天有23小时零56分钟
There were 23 hours and 56 minutes in a stellar day.
查尔斯·查克·克兰兹
39个非凡岁月！
谢谢你
查克！
还零几秒钟
Plus a few odd seconds.
你说的是过去吧？
There "were"?
根据我的计算...
Based on my calculations,
相信我 我的数学很好
which I assure you I can back up, my math is good,
现在一天有24小时零2分钟长
there are now 24 hours and two minutes in a day.
知道这什么意思？
Do you know what that means?
地球自转速度在减慢？
Well, you're saying the Earth's rotation is slowing down?
没错
Exactly.
很多人将这些灾难归咎于我们破坏环境
Lot of folks think all of these disasters are 'cause of what we've done to the environment.
并非如此
Not so.
我先承认 我们对待母亲非常坏
I'm the first to admit, we treated our mother,
是的 地球母亲 万物之母
yes, she's our mother, all of us, very badly.
我们肯定玷污了她 几近强暴
Certainly molested her, if not outright raped her.
但比起宇宙那浩瀚机制 我们只不过是一粒尘埃
But... we're puny compared to the great clock of the universe.
是呀
No.
不论是什么原因
Whatever's happening
问题绝对比环境恶化更大
is much larger than environmental degradation.
这就是数学告诉我的
The math says so.
数学能做很多事
And, and math can do a lot of things.
数学可以是门艺术 但数学可不会撒谎
I mean, math can be art... but it can't lie.
丰收里小区
你看 我要先坐会儿
You know what? I think I'll sit
边欣赏日落 边歇歇脚
and enjoy the sunset while I wait for the arthritis to settle a bit.
要一起坐会儿吗？
You care to join me?
我还想继续走
I think I'll go on.
你前妻 我理解
The ex. I understand.
好的 一路顺风 安德森先生
Well, it was nice speaking with you, Mr. Anderson.
你好
Hey.
别怕 我正去我前妻那儿 菲莉西娅·安德森
Don't worry. I'm going to see my ex-wife, Felicia Anderson.
她现在改回娘家姓戈登了
I think she's back to Gordon now.
她住在费恩巷19号
She lives on Fern Lane, number 19.
是的 我认识戈登小姐
Yeah, I know Miss Gordon.
你大晚上出来干嘛？
What are you doing out?
溜旱冰
I wanted to go skating.
以前我特别喜欢溜旱冰
I used to love skating.
那现在就该就去溜
Then you should go skating.
也许我真该去溜
Maybe I should.
你都跟戈登小姐分手了 咋还去见她？
Why do you see Miss Gordon if she's your ex?
我还是喜欢她
I still like her.
你们吵架吗？
Do you fight?
以前吵
We used to.
分手后 我们相处得更好了
We get along better now that we're exes.
戈登小姐有时会来送她烤的姜饼干
Miss Gordon gives us gingersnap cookies sometimes.
我其实更喜欢奥利奥 不过...
I like Oreos better, but...
就像是盒巧克力 不能每颗都合心意 对吧？
That's just the way the cookie crumbles, right?
姜饼干里没巧克力
Gingersnaps don't crumble.
除非和奥利奥一起吃...
At least not until you crunch them...
你抓紧回家吧
You better go home, I guess.
没路灯 天太黑 没法溜
It's too dark for skating without streetlights.
会没事吗？
Is everything gonna be okay?
当然会
Sure it is.
谢谢你
查克！
回家去
Go home.
回家去找你爸妈
Go home to your Mom and Dad.
抓紧
Do it now.
哦 谢天谢地 谢天谢地
Oh, thank God. Oh, thank God.
-谢天谢地 -这些都 都...
-Thank God. -They, they just...
这些都突然冒出来了
They just, they just started showing up.
我知道 我知道 我也看到了
No, I know, I know, I saw.
只是这个小区吗？
Is it just here?
我觉得到处都有
I think it's everywhere.
看起来时候到了
I think it's almost...
是啊
Yeah...
是的 时候到了
Yeah, I think it's almost...
这是我见过的最亮的星空
It's the brightest I've ever seen the stars.
看那里
Just look at that.
那是天鹰座
There's Aquila the eagle.
嗯
Mm-hm.
那是...
There's, uh...
天鹅座
Cygnus the swan.
你看到了吗？
You see it?
那是北极...
And there's the North Sta...
你看到刚才那个吗？
Did you just see that?
看到了
Yeah.
火星也没了
There goes Mars.
我好怕
I'm scared.
我也是
I am too.
没事的 亲爱的
It's okay, honey.
你先走一步
You go on.
我们到那里再重逢
You go on ahead, okay?
活了才39年
Just thirty-nine years.
是39个非凡岁月
Thirty-nine great years.
谢谢你 查克
Thanks, Chuck.
我爱...
I love y...
第二幕
街头艺人万岁
多亏她那开着旧面包车的朋友麦克帮忙
With the help of her friend, Mac, who has an old van,
泰勒·弗兰克才能把架子鼓摆到
Taylor Franck sets up her drum kit in
第八街长廊上她最喜欢的那个地方
her favored spot on the Eighth Street Promenade.
这天是周四下午
It's Thursday afternoon.
这天的天气 真是绝了
The weather is fucking gorgeous,
街上人来人往 大家都在幻想着周末
and the streets are thronged with people looking forward to the weekend,
毕竟幻想总比现实好
which is always better than the weekend itself.
-泰勒 都差不多了吧？ -嗯 谢了
-All good. Taylor? -Yeah, thanks.
老铁 别忘分我一成收入
Ten percent is all the thanks I want, dude.
泰勒和麦克都在城堡街的心疗唱片店打零工
Taylor, and Mac too, work part-time at Doctor Records on Castle Street.
打赏多时 泰勒挣得差不多跟打零工一样
But on a good day Taylor can make almost as much busking.
魔 术 帽
每笔打赏都会
精彩翻倍!
茱莉亚学院是世界顶尖的音乐学校
当初考上 茱莉亚 时 她爸妈可没料到她会上街打鼓
Busk-drumming isn't what her parents saw for her when she enrolled at Juilliard,
更不知道她现在还辍了学
and they don't know yet that she dropped out.
在茱莉亚他们教你多动脑子
Juilliard wanted you to think about what you were doing,
在泰勒眼里 跟着鼓点走就对了 多想一下灵感就跑了
but as far as Taylor is concerned, the beat is your friend and thinking is the enemy.
她先热身 一开始节奏简单
She starts warming up, going easy at first.
节奏缓慢 不敲牛铃
slow tempo, no cowbell,
不在乎魔术帽空着 里面只有她自己放的钱
not minding that the magic hat stays empty except for her two crumpled dollars
还有个滑板小子随随便便丢进去的硬币
and a quarter flipped contemptuously by a dude on a skateboard.
时间还早 总能找到切入点
There is time. There is a way in.
找到切入点才是占最大头的乐趣
Finding the in is half the fun. Maybe even most of it.
珍妮丝·哈利迪在书店工作一天后正在回家
Janice Halliday is on her way home from seven hours at Paper and Page,
大概会去海边走走
and may walk all the way to the ocean.
谈了一年多的男友刚甩了她
Her boyfriend of 16 months just broke up with her,
随便发个消息甩了她
and he did it the modern way.
女：怎么不回我消息了？
男：咱俩不合适
男：你是个好人
男：继续做朋友？？
王八蛋！
Motherfucker!
这突如其来 犹如当头一棒把门关在脸上
It was totally unexpected, like having a door slammed in your face just as you were getting ready to walk through it.
-那感觉... -真他妈离谱
-It was... -Fucking bullshit!
...真他妈离谱
...fucking bullshit.
她从没动过真情 也没天真地以为自己爱过他
She isn't in love with him. never even kidded herself that she was.
-但依然... -他喵的糟透了
-But still it... -Fucking sucks.
...打她个措手不及
...is a dismaying shock just the same.
她打算回家后喝点酒 顺便哭一场
She supposes she'll have some wine when she gets home and cry.
说不定还会播个爵士乐 在屋里醉舞一番
Maybe queue up one of her big band playlists and dance drunk around the room.
她读高中时就爱跳舞
She loved to dance in high school.
也许能借此重温当年那份快乐
Maybe she can recapture a little of that happiness.
-去你妈的 -你说什么？
-Fucking really?! -Excuse me.
对不起 对不起 没说你 没说你
Sorry, sorry, sorry. Not you, not you.
他喵的！
Fuck!
查克的拿铁好了
Got an oat milk latte for Chuck.
查 克  ^v^
查尔斯·查克·克兰兹
Charles Krantz,
在朋友眼中 他总一身会计行头
Chuck to his friends, is dressed in the armor of accountancy.
灰西装 蓝衬衣配蓝领带
Gray suit, blue shirt, blue tie.
脚上那双温莎牌皮鞋虽不贵 却耐穿
His Samuel Windsor shoes are inexpensive but sturdy.
他来这参加个主题为“二十一世纪银行业”的研讨会
He's here for a week-long conference titled "Banking in the 21st Century."
他的中西部信托银行派他来的
He's been sent by his bank, Midwest Trust,
全程报销
all expenses paid.
查克对嘉宾和座谈都挺有兴趣
Chuck has enjoyed the speakers and the panels.
他上过一个座谈会
He was on one panel
明天中午大会结束前还要再参加一个
and is scheduled to be on another before the conference ends at noon tomorrow,
但他可不想下班后还和那群同行混在一起
but has no wish to spend his off-duty hours in the company of 70 other accountants.
他精通会计的那套行话 也觉得自己能融入别的圈子
He speaks their language, but likes to think he speaks others as well.
至少曾经那么自信 如今却大不如前了
At least he did, although some of the vocabulary is now lost.
现在 他穿着他温莎牌牛津鞋正在午后散步
Now, his sensible Samuel Windsor Oxfords are taking him for an afternoon walk.
现在的生活没能达到最初的设想
His life is narrower than the one he once hoped for,
可他已经释然了
but he's made peace with that.
他明白水往低处流是自然规律
He understands that narrowing is the natural order of things.
他有个忠贞不渝的妻子叫珍妮
He has a wife, Ginny,to whom he is scrupulously faithful,
还有个聪明风趣的儿子上初中
and an intelligent, good-humored son in middle school.
他还有九个月可活 只不过他还不知道
He also has only nine months to live, though he doesn't know that yet.
泰勒已经敲了十分钟了 分文未得 毫无灵感
Taylor has been on the job for 10 minutes now and has nothing to show for it.
她看见个西装男朝她走来
She sees a Mr. Businessman type coming toward her
不知为何 他身上有股气息
and something about him, God knows what,
让泰勒忍不住大张旗鼓宣布他登场了
makes Taylor want to announce his approach.
她先用松弛的摇摆热场 又切换到更撩人的节奏
She slips first into a reggae beat, then something slinkier.
今天头一次 泰勒火花被点燃
And for the first time today, Taylor feels a spark
便在核心鼓点上敲着牛铃
and begins to whack the cowbell on the downbeat.
真带感
It's pretty cool.
鼓点已经到来 那律动带你一路向前
The groove has arrived, and the groove is like a road you want to follow.
她本可把节拍提快 玩点花样
She could speed the beat up, get some tom in there,
但此刻目光是那西装男 多此一举反而不搭
but she's watching Mr. Businessman and that seems wrong for this dude.
她以为那西装男只是路过 要去商务酒店
She believes Mr. Businessman will just go on past on his way to the business hotel,
等他一走 泰勒再换节拍
and when he's gone, Taylor will switch to something else.
可他却停下脚步
But instead of floating on by...
赏个脸
Come on.
来吧 小老妹
Come on, little sister.
跳个舞吧
Let's dance.
跳
Dance.
对了
Yeah!
我带你跳 有我别怕
I'll lead you. I got you.
啊
Uh.
没事 眼镜的事儿 眼镜的事儿
It's okay. It's my glasses. It's my glasses.
现在该做什么？
What are we doing?
我也不知道
I don't know.
大伙 今天就到这了
No more today, folks.
今天就到这了
No more today.
今天就到这了 得见好就收
No more today. We gotta quit while we're ahead.
魔 术 帽
每笔打赏都会
精彩翻倍!
要搭把手吗
Do you need a-any help at all or...
好 帮把这个收起来
Here, can you, uh, take this?
-好 -拧这里
-Sure. -Just, just spin the thingy here.
-小心别夹手了 -会雨过天晴的
But watch out for your fingers. -It'll, it'll, it'll get 'em good.
懂了吧
you know what I mean?
-好 好 -找点事散散心
-Yeah, yeah. -To doing something else.
刚太神奇了
What just happened?
跳的太神了
That was incredible.
你们是舞蹈演员吗？
You dance for a living?
哦 不 不
No. Oh, no. I...
-不 不是的 -你做什么的？
-No, I do not, sir. -What do you do for a living?
哎呦 我好像不小心搞坏了
Oh, no, I think I... Did I... I didn't break it, did I?
这个好像坏了
I think he broke it.
去喷泉吧
Let's hit the pond.
那儿没停车位
We'll never find parking by the Common.
那也要停
We will today.
今天 就像魔术一样
Today...is magic.
你们在哪练的这身舞功？
Where did you learn to dance like that?
别 别 别 那是你赚的
Oh, no, no, no, that's yours.
不 有福同享
Nope, we split it even.
要我自己敲 一天也赚不了这么多
By myself, I wouldn't have made half as much if I drummed till midnight.
你没事吧？
You okay?
还好
Yeah.
就是有点头疼
Yeah. Just one of my headaches.
不了 不了 真用不着 你留着吧
Oh, no, no, no. Come on. I don't need it. You keep it.
来吧 老兄 你应得的
Come on, man, you earned it.
拿去吃顿饭 转手送人也行 但这钱我偏要交给你
Buy yourself dinner. Give it away. But I'm handing it to you.
你们干这行都能当职业了
You could do this for a living, you know?
我可不敢这么说
I don't know about that.
我真觉得靠街头表演 我们能红 能赚大钱
I really think we could busk our way to fame and fortune.
你怎么会停在我面前？
What made you stop in front of me?
又为什么突然跳起舞？
Why did you start moving?
他本可以说 鼓点让他想起了他那不成气候的追旧青年乐队
He could say it was because he was thinking about his old half-assed band, The Retros,
还有他多么的喜欢跟着节奏跳舞
and how he liked to dance across the stage during instrumental breaks.
但他没这么说
But that's not it.
我也说不清
I don't know.
泰勒 该走了
Taylor, we gotta roll,
不然你赚的钱都得交罚单了
or you're gonna end up spending your take on my parking ticket.
你们不考虑转行跳舞吗？
So, you guys don't want a career change?
转行？
Career change? How... I mean...
我们肯定能闯出名堂
We'll make a name for ourselves.
别急着走 先进来一下
You got to get in here before you go.
-来个大团抱！ -哦 哦 好
-Group hug. -Oh, oh, okay.
-大团抱！ -来
-Group hug. -Okay.
快 快 快
Go.
来 来
Come on.
街头艺人万岁
Buskers forever.
好了 好了
Yeah. Buskers forever.
得赶在贴罚单前抓紧走
We gotta roll before the meter maid shows up.
真替你难过
I'm so sorry.
真倒霉
That sucks.
这确实倒霉
It does suck.
我真觉得他人还不错
I thought he was a nice guy.
床上功夫也到位 我们在一起挺开心的
He was a pretty good lover, and we had fun and all that.
我回去得找下我们跳舞的视频 估计会上热搜
If I can find a video of us dancing, which I'm gonna look because I bet we go viral,
然后转发给他 再附句“这就是你错过的缘分”
I'm gonna send it to him with a text, a text that says, "This is what you're missing."
你会没事的
You're gonna be fine.
我不是全都懂 可这件事我很清楚
I don't know a lot, but I know that much.
光辉就在你前面 往前迈一步乌云就消散
You got a bright sunbeam in front of you, and you're gonna step right into it, I can tell.
但现在
But yeah.
真倒霉 没啥好说的
It sucks. Not much else to say.
一切都完了 我们也只剩下句真倒霉
Everything goes down the drain, and all we can say is, "That sucks."
对
Yeah.
说不定谁都躲不掉这劫
Maybe we're going down the drain too.
说不定
Maybe.
我走这条路
I'm this way.
我往那边走
Uh, I'm that way.
多谢你陪我跳舞
Thank you for the dance.
当他走过泰勒摆鼓的地方
As he passes the place where Taylor set up her drums,
那两个问题又冒了出来
those two questions recur.
为什么要停下脚步听？
Why did he stop to listen?
又为什么要跳起舞？
And why did he start to dance?
他自己也想不通
He doesn't know.
就算真有答案能够让这段回忆更动人吗？
And would answers make a good thing better?
后来 他走路都成问题
Later, he'll lose the ability to walk,
和那个小老妹跳舞成了个传说
never mind dancing with little sister on the promenade.
再后来 他咀嚼都成了难题
Later, he'll lose the ability to chew food.
再后来 他记不住妻子的名字
Later, he'll forget his wife's name.
到最后 他分不清白日黑夜
Later, he'll lose his grip on the difference between waking and sleeping
陷入一种让人质疑生命意义的巨大痛苦中
and enter a land of pain so great he will wonder why God made the world.
但有时 他还会记得当初把公文包一丢
What he will remember, occasionally, is how he stopped and dropped his briefcase
跟着鼓点起舞的感觉
and began to move his hips to the beat of the drums.
他会觉得 这就是上帝让世界存在的意义
And he will think that is why God made the world.
仅此而已
Just that.
第一幕
我包罗万象
查克一直盼着能有个小妹妹
Chuck was looking forward to having a baby sister.
更盼着父母能赶紧回来
Of course, he was also looking forward to having parents,
谁料95号高架上结的冰让一切化为泡影
but none of that worked out thanks to a patch 95 of well-hidden ice on an I-95 overpass.
事发时查克没在车上
Chuck wasn't in the car when it happened
他父母去享受二人世界
because his parents were having a dinner date
那天晚上他爷爷奶奶带他
and he was being babysat by his grandparents,
他那会儿还叫他们阿爷阿奶
who, at the time, he was still calling Zaydee and Bubbie.
他那时七岁了
He was seven years old.
真赞喔
Excellent job.
一年半载 屋子里全是悲伤
For a year and a half, it was a house of unadulterated sadness.
对阿尔比和莎拉·克兰兹来说 不只是儿子和儿媳没了
Albie and Sarah Krantz had not only lost their son and daughter-in-law...
咋不吃饭了？
Why're you not eating?
那本该三个月后出生的孙女也没了
...they had lost the granddaughter who would've been born just three months later.
咋回事儿？
What's going on?
名字都选好了...
The name had already been picked out...
-她叫艾雨莎 -艾雨莎
-Her name is Alyssa. -...Alyssa.
查克说那名字听着像下雨时
When Chuck said that sounded to him like rain,
他妈哭笑不得
his mother had laughed and cried at the same time.
他永远忘不了那表情
He never forgot that.
阿尔比靠两件事来排解悲伤
Albie processed his grief by turning to his two absolutes,
算账和喝酒
numbers and alcohol.
但对莎拉来说 一切却都失去了滋味
Sarah, though, could find no joy in her usual pleasures.
曾让她陶醉的音乐 艺术和美食
She loved the flavors of life, music, art, and food,
如今都索然无味
but now, found the world quiet and gray and flavorless.
随着时间流逝 家里又慢慢有了些温暖
Some of the good feelings came back into the house with time.
事故后全靠外卖度日
There were a lot of takeout meals after the accident,
但查克快十岁那年 他奶奶又重新下厨
but around the time Chuck turned 10, his grandma started cooking again.
她做饭时爱放摇滚乐
She liked rock-and-roll while she was cooking.
查克肯定觉得太潮了 可她显然乐在其中
Music Chuck would've thought much too young for her, but which she clearly enjoyed.
来吧 小老弟 来跳舞吧
Come on, little brother, let's dance.
《西区故事》
《雨中曲》
《歌厅》
《爵士春秋》
《封面女郎》
电影《封面女郎》(1944)
小宝 你有本事学会 你天生是跳舞的料
You could learn those moves, kiddo. You're a natural.
你在哪学的？
Wh-Where did you learn?
高中
High school.
你上高中的时候是什么样的？
What were you like in high school?
我可是个小辣妹
I was a kusit.
千万别把我这话告诉你阿爷哦
But don't you tell your Zaydee I said that.
他是个老古董
He's old school, that one.
查克守口如瓶
Chuck never told.
他把爷爷奶奶家处处都当自己家
His grandparents' house became every inch his home
除了塔尖阁楼
with one exception. the cupola on the roof.
查克被严令禁止进那阁楼
Chuck was forbidden to go into the cupola.
那是他爷爷的一条铁律 不容置疑
That was his grandfather's rule, and it was absolute, emphatic.
他爷爷阿尔比做事宽容
Albie wasn't a stern man in other matters.
平时人挺温和的
He was downright gentle in most respects.
偏偏在这事上绝不讲情面
But on this point, he was rigid.
查克可不止问过一次
Chuck asked about it, of course, and more than once.
那上头有什么？从高高的窗户能看到啥？
What was up there? What could you see from the high window?
最重要的是 为啥老是锁着？
And the big question, why was the room locked?
他奶奶说...
Grandma said...
楼上地板不结实 一踩就会坍下去
Because the floor isn't safe and you might go right through it.
他爷爷说...
Grandpa said...
由于那烂地板 屋子里空无一物
There's nothing up there because of that rotten floor.
你往窗外瞅 也就只能看到商场
And the only thing you can see through the windows is the shopping center.
他一直这么说 直到查克十一岁生日前一晚
He said that until, one night, just before Chuck's 11th birthday,
他才吐出部分实情
when he told at least part of the truth.
宇宙历年法
The cosmic calendar
把宇宙的历史压缩到一本365天日历
compresses the local history of the universe into a single year.
从1月1日宇宙诞生算起
If the universe began on January 1st,
我们的银河系要到5月才出现
it was not until May that the Milky Way formed.
俗话说酒后吐真言
Drinking is not good for secrets.
当儿子 儿媳还有那个名字听着像下雨的
And after the death of his son, daughter-in-law, and granddaughter-to-be,
未来孙女艾雨莎全都去世后
Alyssa, who sounds like rain,
阿尔比·克兰兹就拼命喝酒
Albie Krantz drank a great deal.
人类全部的历史 都在
Everything humans have ever done occurred in that bright speck
这本日历的最后一天
at the lower right of the cosmic calendar.
我打赌 从阁楼往外看 能看到西福商场
I'll bet you could see way past the Westford Mall from the cupola.
整座小镇肯定也能看得一清二楚
You gotta be able to see the whole town from up there, I bet.
要真上去了 你看见的可不只是风景
If you went up there, you might see a lot more than you wanted.
小查 这门紧锁是有原因的
That's why it's locked, Chucko.
日历里每个月代表12.5亿年
Every month is one and a quarter billion years long.
每一天代表4000万年
Each day represents 40 million years.
他想问清楚
He wanted to ask what Grandpa meant.
尽管他才10岁
But the adult part of him, not there in person, no, not at 10,
可脑子里的成熟声音冒出来
but something that had begun to speak on rare occasions,
告诉他别吭声 安静地等着
told him to be quiet. Be quiet and wait.
人类的全部历史就像我手掌那么大
But all of human history would occupy an area the size of my hand.
现在让我们回到太古时代...
We're just beginning to trace the long and tortuous path which began with the primeval...
你知道这房子是什么风格的吗？
You know what style of house this is?
维多利亚风格
Victorian.
没错
That's right.
可不是仿古的 1885年建的正经维多利亚式
And not pretend Victorian either. It was built in 1885.
后来翻新过大概六次吧
It's been remodeled half a dozen times since.
可那阁楼一直保留至今
But that cupola was there from the start.
我七十年代初搬来
Been here since '71.
搬来至今 我上那阁楼都没到六次
And in all those years, I haven't been up to that damn cupola half a dozen times.
因为地板烂了？
'Cause the floor is rotted?
因为闹鬼
'Cause it's full of ghosts.
...发生在12月31日的晚上10点30分
...around 10:30 p.m. on December 31st.
-还记得圣诞述异那个故事吗？ -嗯
-Y-You remember Scrooge? -Yeah.
那部叫做《圣诞欢歌》的电影？
That Scrooge movie we watched?
记得
I remember.
你觉得那算鬼故事吗？
Do you think of that as a ghost story?
应该算吧
I-I-I guess so.
有人说那是鬼故事
Heard someone say it was a ghost story.
他吓的说“圣诞节未卜先知”
Christmas Yet to Come.
晚上11点59分20秒...
11:59:20，evening, last day of the...
杰弗里家那男孩一个月后就没了
Jefferies boy was a month later.
亨利·彼得森拖得久些 等了四五年
Henry Peterson, that took longer. Four...maybe five years on.
到那时 阁楼里看到的 我几乎忘得精光
And by then...I almost forgot what I saw up there.
几乎
Almost.
我说过再也不上去
Said I'd never go back up there after that.
真不想上去 要不是为了莎拉
And I wish I hadn't because of Sarah.
为了你的阿奶 小查
Because of your Bubbie, Chucky.
最疼你的阿奶
Your sweet Bubbie.
都是面包
And the bread.
我们听说过的所有人...
Every person we've ever heard of, somewhere in there...
这就是等待 小查
It's the waiting, Chucko.
这是最难熬的
That's the hard part.
所有历史书上的事 都只...
Everything in the history books happended...
发生在这本日历最后10秒钟里
here in the last 10 seconds of the cosmic calendar.
呜 外面真冷
Ooh! It's getting cold out there.
维拉向大家问好 还感谢我煲的汤
Vera says hi. She says thanks for the soup.
她把八卦全抖给我 抖得可带劲了
She laid the gossip on me, laid it good.
当然 要不然咱咋离不开她呢
Of course...That's why we have a Vera, isn't it?
有什么新鲜事吗？
So, what's the latest?
不知道你听说了没 凯伦和马蒂在搞婚姻咨询
Well, I don't know if you've heard, but Trish is saying Karen and Matty are in therapy.
-搞什么？ -阿爷 亨利·彼得森到底是谁？
-Again. -Who's Henry Peterson, Zaydee?
...珍惜我们的宇宙 不要辜负这150亿年
...the universe that made us or we can squander our 15 billion-year heritage.
再买点煎饼粉
And get some pancake mix.
要黄盒的 别买橙盒的 都记住了吗？
Yellow box, not the orange box. You got all that?
记住了
I got it.
-要我写下来吗？ -我记得住
-Do you need me to write it down? -I got it.
别开车 走路去能醒醒酒
Don't you think about driving. The walk will sober you up.
好 好 好
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
他去便利店了 一会儿就回来
He'll be back with some groceries.
要不今晚一起烤棉花糖？
Then, how about tonight, we do some s'mores in the fireplace?
随便
Yeah.
好吧
他是不是跟你说闹鬼的事了？
Was he blabbing to you about his ghosts?
阁楼里闹鬼的事？
The ones that live in the cupola?
是呀
Yeah.
是真的吗？
Well, are there?
你说呢？
What do you think?
别太信你阿爷
I wouldn't pay too much attention to Zaydee.
他人不错 就是有时喝得太多
He's a good man. But, sometimes, well, sometimes, he drinks too much.
喝多了就会天马行空 你懂他那一套
Then he rides his hobby horses. I'm sure you know what I'm talking about.
杰弗里家男孩是谁？
Who was the Jefferies boy?
好吧 小宝 那是件让人心酸的事
Well...that was a very sad thing, kiddo.
他住旁边那巷子
He lived on the next block over,
追球追到马路上结果被车撞了
and he got hit by a car when he chased a ball into the street.
那是很久前的事儿了
It happened a long time ago.
要是你爷爷说他提前见过那一幕 他并没有
And if your grandpa says he saw it before it happened, he's mistaken.
那只是他酒后乱说
He just drinks too much.
要不我帮你送到史坦利奶奶那儿？
You know, I could take those to Mrs. Stanley if you want.
哎呀 你真贴心 维拉看到你肯定特开心
Oh, that's very thoughtful of you. I bet Vera'd love that.
简直绝了
Just wonderful.
你奶奶真是个烘焙大师
Your, your grandmother is an artist.
谢谢你带来 你主动要来送的吧？
Thank you for bringing them over. Was that your idea?
-说实话哦 -是的
-Be honest. -It was.
要喝茶吗？
Well, can I make you a cup of tea?
其实我不喝茶 有杯牛奶就完美了
Um, I don't drink tea, but, um, I wouldn't mind a glass of milk.
你奶奶真是个大好人
Well, your grandmother's a saint.
你爷爷呢？
And what about your granddad?
他背上那东西去检查了吗？
Did he have that thing on his back looked at?
嗯 医生拿掉了 还做了化验
Yeah, the, the doctor took it off and had it tested.
全告诉我
Tell me everything.
不是坏的那种
It wasn't one of the bad ones.
谢天谢地
Thank God for that.
嗯
Yeah.
他跟奶奶聊那个叫亨利·彼得森的人
He, um, he was talking to Grandma about someone named Henry Peterson.
太惨了
So awful.
亨利跟你爷爷一样是管账的
You know, Henry was a bookkeeper, just like your granddad.
还接了镇上你阿爷扛不下的活儿...
He did a lot of the other businesses in town. The ones that your Zaydee didn't do...
到底怎么回事？
How did it happen?
这种事你还是别听了
I don't think you want to hear about that stuff.
呃 爷爷说 说那很平和
Um, w-w-well, Granddad said it was, uh, peaceful.
平和？
Peaceful?
他自尽了 上吊的
He killed himself. Hung himself.
他老婆跟个刚满十八的小伙子私奔了
His wife, you see, she ran off with this younger man, barely old enough to vote.
她自己都四十多了 你怎么看？
And she was in her 40s. What do you think of that?
-天哪 -对 可不是
-Wow. -Damn right, wow.
我还听说...
And then, I heard that...
学校那边有什么新鲜事？
What's happening at school?
谁和谁在亲亲啦？
Who's smooching who?
放心说吧 无人能闻得见 我只多留片刻
"Talk honestly, for no one else hears you and I stay only a minute longer."
我是否自相矛盾？
"Do I contradict myself?
好吧 那我就自相矛盾
"Very well then, I contradict myself,"
我心疆无限 我包罗万象
"I am large. I contain multitudes."
六年级的最后一堂课上
On the last day of sixth grade,
那位小清新气息 管不住课堂的理查兹老师
Miss Richards, a sweet, hippie-dippyish young woman who had no command of discipline
怕是很快就要被劝退
and would probably not last long in the public education system,
还是在查克班上照念惠特曼《自我之歌》的诗
tried to recite for Chuck's class some verse of Walt Whitman's "Song of Myself."
若最初寻我不得 莫失信心
"Failing to fetch me at first keep encouraged.
错过此处 再觅它方
Missing me one place, search another."
这节课还算顺利 对吧？
That went well, don't you think?
嗯 让您为难了
Yeah, I'm, I'm sorry about that.
惠特曼那句“我心疆无限 我包罗万象”是啥意思？
What does he mean when he says, "I am large, I contain multitudes"?
你觉得他想表达什么？
What do you think he means?
包罗他认识的所有人
All the people he knows.
对
Yes.
但也许不止于此
But maybe he means even more.
来 过来
Here. Come here.
我的两手之间 那里有什么？
What's in there? Between my hands?
我头
My brain.
不 不是这个意思
No, um, that's not exactly what I mean.
我是说 在我两手之间 里面装的是什么
What's in there? Right between my hands right now.
我不知道
I don't know.
里面有你认识的所有人吗？
All the people you know?
有吧
I guess.
就只有你认识的人吗？
Just the people you know?
里面是你见过的记住的一切
Everything you see. Everything you know.
是整个世界 查克
The world, Chuck.
天上的飞机 地上的井盖
Planes in the sky. Manhole covers in the street.
年复一年 你脑海中的世界
Every year that you live, that world inside your head
会越来越大 越鲜明 越丰富 越复杂
will get bigger and brighter and more detailed and complex.
你会在脑海中构建城市 国家 大陆
You will build cities and countries and continents,
并用真实和想象的人去充实那里
and you will fill them with people and faces, real and imagined.
明白了吗？
Do you understand?
别就此止步
Don't stop there.
把你见过的 认识的
You fill the whole thing with everyone you ever meet,
甚至想象的每个人都给装进去
everyone you ever know, everyone you ever just imagine.
它就变成了个小宇宙
It'll be a universe.
整个宇宙就在我两手之间
A whole universe right between my hands.
你能包罗万象
You contain multitudes.
那...
So...
那个宇宙会怎样 要是有人...
what happens to that universe if someone...
比如说...
I don't know,
在冰面上打滑 冲下高架桥 或者...
hits a patch of ice and goes off an overpass or...
别太纠结这些
Don't worry too much about those things.
只要记住 你包罗万象 查克
Just remember that you contain multitudes, Chuck.
这多棒啊
Isn't that wonderful?
好了 就这样 你真是个好孩子
Now, go on. You were such a good boy.
能教你我很开心
I've really enjoyed having you in class.
查克暑假本来过得挺好 直到八月
Chuck did enjoy his summer until August,
他阿奶去世了
when Bubbie died.
事情发生在街角的便利店里
It happened at the grocery store down the street,
公开场合 有点不太体面
in public, which was a little undignified,
至少这种死法能让人安心地说...
but at least it was the kind of death where people can safely say...
幸好她一生没受什么罪
Thank God she didn't suffer.
至于那句...
The other standby...
她一生又长又圆满
She had a long, full life.
就说不准了
...was more of a gray area.
毕竟她才六十多岁
Sarah Krantz had yet to reach her mid-60s.
又一次 家里再次陷入彻底的悲伤
Once more, the house on Pilchard Street was one of unadulterated sadness.
阿尔比戴上了黑纱 越发消瘦
Albie wore his mourning band, and lost weight,
也不再讲笑话了
and stopped telling his jokes
比他实际七十岁还显老
and began to look older than his 70 years.
-就买这点？ -嗯
-That's it? -Yeah.
一块七毛五
Buck 75.
几周前来的那个女士 就是后来去世的那位
Um, that lady who was in here a few weeks ago, the one who died.
事情发生在哪儿？
Where was she when it happened?
小朋友 这话题有点吓人
That's a little creepy, kid.
她是我奶奶
She was my grandma.
她当时想拿面包
She was getting a loaf of bread.
结果把整排货架都拽倒砸她身上了
Pulled down almost everything on the shelf when she collapsed.
要是我说多了 你别介意
I'm sorry if that's too much information.
没事
Nah.
我早知道了
I already knew that.
-别！ -啥？
-No! -What?!
-走开 快走开 -等下
-Get away from there! You get away from there. -What? Hey, hey!
把锁给我
Give me that.
给我 给我
Give it to me. Give it to me.
抓紧给我
Give me it.
哦 对不起
Oh. Oh, I'm sorry.
对不起
I'm sorry.
你没受伤吧
Are you okay?
你看到了什么？
What did you see?
到底看到了什么？
对不起 你不能去那里
I'm sorry. It's just, you can't.
绝不能去那里 小查
You can't do that, Chucky.
绝不能
You just can't.
哦 我真对不起
Oh, I'm so sorry.
哦 对不起 真的 真是对不起
Oh, I'm sorry. I'm so, so sorry. I'm sorry.
课后兴趣班纳新
游泳社团
舞蹈社团
数学竞赛社
读书会
舞蹈社团
舞侠们 来跳舞吧
来吧 小老弟 来跳舞吧
Come on, little brother. Let's dance.
舞侠们 舞者们 大家好
Hello, twirlers, and hello, spinners.
哎呦 今年居然有三个男孩 破纪录了
What do you know? Three boys this year. It's a new record.
小先生们别怕被取笑
You gentlemen might find yourselves being teased for your new hobby.
我保证 你们是全校最聪明的
I assure you, you are the smartest young men in the whole school.
待会儿你们就明白了
You'll soon see what I mean.
不认识我的同学们 我是罗巴赫老师
For those who don't know me, I am Miss Rohrbacher.
在女子体育课外 我被尊称为...
And when I'm not teaching the girls phys-ed,  I am what a few students have called,
舞林怪才
"The Dance Monster."
没反应？好吧
Nothing? Alright.
你们加入的社团堪称学校最牛的
You have chosen what might be the best club this school has ever had.
与女排社团并驾齐驱
'Cause if we didn't have girls volleyball, we wouldn't have nothing.
不 不 不
No, no, no.
回来 马尔福同学 你现在归我管了
Back, Mr. Mulford, you are mine now.
华尔兹
Waltz.
查克会跳
Chuck knew it.
恰恰舞
Cha-cha.
查克也会跳
Chuck knew it.
摇摆舞
Swing.
三拍步 摇摆步
Triple step. Rock step.
查克还会跳
Chuck knew it.
三拍步 摇摆步
Triple step. Rock step.
桑巴舞
Samba.
没跳过这个
Don't know that one.
他是这小社团里跳的最好的
He was, by far, the best dancer in the little club.
老师常让他和不会跳的女生搭档
So, Miss Rohrbacher mostly put him with the girls who were clumsy.
他明白老师的用意 也乐意帮忙
He understood she did it to make them better, and he was a good sport about it.
快下课前
Near the end of their two hours, however,
舞林怪才才心软 让他和凯特·麦考伊搭档
The Dance Monster would show mercy and pair him with Cat McCoy,
她八年级 也是所有女生里跳得最溜的
who was an eighth grader and the best dancer of the girls.
查克可没动她的心思
Chuck didn't expect romance.
卡特确实漂亮 不过也比他高一头
Cat was not only gorgeous, she was a full foot taller than he was.
但他很喜欢和她一起跳 她也有同感
But he loved to dance with her, and the feeling was mutual.
...外 二 三 转
...three. Out, two, three. Switch.
好 停
And stop.
内 二 三 外 二 三
In, two, three. Out, two, three.
转 换箱步
Turn. Now box.
一 二 三 一 二 三
One, two, three. One, two, three.
看 你 们 跳 的 啥
I don't know what that is.
老 天 呐
Oh, my God.
算了 自由练十分钟
Okay, 10 minutes freestyle.
嘿 瞧好
Hey. Watch this.
快教我
Show me how you did that.
看好
Ready?
滑 滑 滑
Slide, slide, slide.
来试试
Here, ready?
来跟我学
Try it with me.
不行 把鞋脱了 穿袜子滑
Uh, kick off your shoes and do it in your socks.
好 好
Aye-aye.
滑右脚
Now, slide.
滑左脚
Slide.
看 你学会了
Yeah. There you go.
来 让我看看
Hey! Show me.
停 滑 停 滑 滑 滑
Pop. Slide. Pop. Slide. Slide. Slide.
再来次
Yeah, again.
停 滑 停
Pop. Slide. Pop.
那天下课晚了半小时
Twirlers and Spinners let out half an hour late that day.
刚太酷了 你自己琢磨出来的吗？
That's so rad. You figured that out by yourself?
我就不断回放 反复看 最终学会的
Well, I just kept rewinding and rewinding 'til I figured it out.
在舞会那天我们一起跳这个吧
We should do that at the Fling.
呃 别误会 才不是要跟你谈恋爱
Uh, not as a date or anything.
我跟道奇·温特沃斯在一起
I'm going out with Dougie Wentworth.
你知道吧？
You know that, right?
知道
Yeah.
可这不妨碍我们露露绝活
But that doesn't mean we couldn't show them some cool moves.
我超想跳 你呢？
I really want to. Do you?
我 我不确定
I-I don't know.
我太矮了
I'm a lot shorter.
人们会笑话我的
I think people will laugh.
-这管用 -确实管用
-That totally works. -It totally does.
-确定吗？ -当然确定
-Are you sure? -Oh, yeah, I'm sure.
感觉很好
Well, they feel great!
就是码有点大
Uh, just a little big.
差不多了
That should be enough.
-再塞点 -再塞点
-Little more. -Maybe one more.
怎么样？
How's that?
就像溜冰一样
Floor feels like ice.
要是把地板刮花 可要被揍
You put scratches on that floor, the janitor is gonna beat y...
蒂米 不会刮花的 他很轻的
Timmy. There won't be no scratches. He's too light on his feet to leave any.
几乎都对了
Almost perfect.
这两题再算一遍
Take another run at these two.
别叹气 你有这方面天赋 知道吗？
You don't need to sigh. You're good at this, you know?
你真的很出色
You're really good at it.
好吧 可这也太枯燥了
Yeah, but it's boring.
枯燥？是说数学吗？
Boring? What, you mean math?
嗯
Yeah.
我觉得你下学期课后应该报个数学竞赛社
I wonder if maybe next semester you might want to try Math League after school.
我整个高中都在参加 特有趣
I did it all high school, in fact, and it was so great.
我现在报的是舞蹈社团
I'm doing Twirlers and Spinners.
对
Yeah.
嘿 先放下笔 先听我说说
Hey, hey, put that down for a second, will you?
说点数学的事
Just a little about math.
人们最初都以为它很枯燥
Because people start out thinking it might be boring,
这就是错在起点
and that's their first mistake.
无论干什么职业 做哪份工作
It's used in every career, in every job,
地球上生活的方方面面都离不开它
in every facet of life on this planet.
毋庸置疑 就连地球自己也离不开它
That's a fact. Hell, the planet.
一天到底有多长？
How do you think we figure out how long a day is?
谁都知道一天有多长
Everybody knows how long a day is.
-多长？ -24小时
-How long? -Twenty-four hours.
大家都说一天有24小时 但这是错的
People say it's 24 hours, but they're wrong.
在恒星日中一天有23小时零56分钟
There are 23 hours and 56 minutes in a stellar day.
还零几秒钟 数学可以证明
Plus a few odd seconds. Math proves it.
怎么知道地球存在多久？
How do we know how old the Earth is?
宇宙存在多久？人类又存在多久？
How old the universe is, how long people have been here?
又怎么建桥 盖楼 测星距
Or how to build a bridge or a skyscraper or how far apart the stars are?
怎么登月的？
How did we land on the moon?
星星是怎么燃烧的？原子怎么聚变裂变的？
The stars themselves. Why they burn, why atoms split and fuse,
这些都离不开数学
and all the rest is just math.
星星本身就是数学产物
Hey, stars are just math.
当你仰望夜空时
When you look at the night sky,
看到的是宇宙最壮丽的方程式
you're seeing the greatest equation in the universe.
更别说你的舞蹈 那也是数学
Heck, your dancing, that's math too.
舞蹈的语言到底是什么？
I mean, what's the language of dance?
你怎么学舞步的？
How do you learn your steps?
名字就在那里 叫数拍
It's even in the name. I mean, they call it "the count."
一 二 三 四
One and two and three and four.
华尔兹呢？一 二 三 一 二 三
What's a waltz? One, two, three, one, two, three.
全是数字 都是数学
Just numbers, just math.
不仅如此
And more than that,
数学可以是门艺术
there's an art to it.
我干的活儿 你看这堆文件 这些档案
What I do, all these files here, all these folders,
记录的都是人们的生活
these are all people's lives.
他们每个选择
Every choice they made.
去年 过去十年
Last year, last 10 years.
他们在意的一切
Everything that's important to them.
所有缺点 嗜好和梦想
Every weakness they have, every vice, every dream,
全都体现在数字里
it's all here in numbers.
要是哪个外行进来 生搬硬算
Some schmuck comes in, takes those numbers,
缺了艺术感 就能害人丢了房子
does the math without artistry, someone loses their house.
而我注入一丝艺术匠心
I take those numbers, do a little art,
便能救人于难
I save someone's life.
这就是会计的魅力
That's what I do.
这就是会计的意义
That's what accounting is.
也许他们该教这些有趣的
Well, maybe they should teach that, the cool stuff,
别教枯燥的
and not just all the boring stuff.
嗯
Hmm.
数学可不止这些
Math is something else too.
像统计学 概率学
Some math, math that's called statistics or probability,
可以未卜先知
it can tell you stuff about your future.
比方说
It could tell you, for example,
你进职业球队的几率
you're more likely to be drafted by a major league sports team
大过靠跳舞谋生
than to make a real living as a dancer.
大家都爱看跳舞 没错
The world loves dancers, it truly does.
可社会更需要会计师
But it needs accountants,
需求大所以机会也多
so there's much more demand, so there's much more opportunity.
我知道这话扎心 但这就是事实
I know that might hurt, but it's the truth.
数学不会撒谎 它只讲事实
Math is truth. It won't lie to you.
数学不掺感情 它就是这么纯粹
It doesn't factor in your preferences. It's pure that way.
数学能做很多事
Math can do a lot of things.
数学可以是门艺术
Math can be art.
但数学可不会撒谎
But it can't lie.
所以...
So...
再把那两题重算一遍吧
take another run at those two because, Chucko,
小查 你很出色
you are good.
你有 艺术细胞
You... have art in you.
嘿！你今天超好看的！
Hey! You look great!
谢谢 你也是
Thanks. Uh, you too.
想不想给他们露两手？
Wanna show 'em how it's done?
这个 我不 我 我可能扭到脚了
Uh, I don't know. I kinda, um...I kinda hurt my leg.
真的假的？
You hurt your leg?
要不 要不 等首更好的歌吧？
Maybe, maybe let's, let's wait for a better song.
嘿 小子
Hey, kiddo.
嘿
Hey.
我以为你今晚要大放异彩呢
Thought you were gonna tear it up tonight.
我 我也不知道
I don't, I don't know.
鞋子怪怪的
My shoes feel all funny,
我 我脚扭了
and... I hurt my leg.
哦 你脚扭了？
Oh, you hurt your leg?
嗯
Yeah.
真替你可惜
I'm sorry to hear that.
你一个人来的？
So, you came stag, huh?
-啥？-没带约会对象？
-Hmm? -No date.
没 我
Nah, I...
情况会变的 相信我 迟早会变 再等等
That'll change. Believe me, it'll change. Just give it some time.
舞池里这些...
None of this, none of...
舞池里这些都不重要
None of that out there really means anything.
跳得怎样 都只是热身和演习 别把它当真
It's all just, just a scrimmage. Just a practice.
嘿 这首正好 来跳吧
Hey, this is perfect. Come on.
不行 我...
Nah, I'm still, uh...
我脚还怪怪的
My leg's still wonky.
查克 得了吧 让我们炸翻全场
Chuck, come on. We're gonna blow the roof off.
对不起
I'm sorry.
真的很痛
It really hurts.
我从八岁就开始跳舞 又教体育
You know, I've been dancing since I was eight, and I teach PE,
看过不少孩子受伤后的样子
and I've seen when my kids get hurt.
他们走路都不一样了
I see how their walk changes.
站姿也怪
I see how their posture changes.
说句实话 在我看来...
And don't mind me saying, but you look...
查克 你看上去好好的
Well, you look fine to me, Chuck.
我没逼你非得跟她跳 决定权在你
I'm not saying that you have to dance with the girl. It's up to you.
我只想说 不管跳不跳 别说谎
I'm just saying dance or no dance, you don't have to lie.
跟她实话实说
Tell her the truth.
她会理解的
She can take it.
-准备好了吗？ -嗯 来跳吧
-You ready? -Yeah. Let's do it.
再跳一遍！再跳一遍！
One more time! One more time!
他们年纪虽小 却足够聪明知道何时收场
They may have been young, but they were smart enough to know when to quit.
谢谢大家
Thank you, guys.
在他39岁因脑瘤早逝前六个月
Six months before he died of a brain tumor at the unfair age of 39,
趁头脑还算清楚
and while his mind was still working, mostly,
他跟妻子珍妮坦白了手背上疤的来历
Chuck told his wife the truth about the scar on the back of his hand.
最开始交往时
When they'd first started dating,
他说这疤是那晚舞会后
he told her he'd gotten it from a boy named Doug Wentworth,
舞伴凯特的男友温特沃斯因为吃醋
who was pissed about him dancing with his girlfriend at a middle school formal
把他推到围栏上铁丝划的
and pushed him into a chain link fence outside the gym.
这疤我没说真话
I lied about that, though.
哇 你还是这么神秘
Oh, my. A man of secrets, even still.
亲爱的 怎么弄的？
What happened, love?
那晚舞跳完
When our fabulous dance was over, I...
我全身又汗又热
I was sweaty and I was so hot.
脸都热得通红
I-I felt like my cheeks were gonna catch fire.
跳的太好了
You were great.
-谢谢 -真是个大明星啊
-Thank you. -What a star.
我那时只想逃离灯光
All I wanted in that moment was just darkness,
吹吹凉风 一个人呆会儿
cool air, and to be by myself.
那晚天空繁星闪烁
There were millions of stars that night.
千万星辰
Millions of them.
千层万叠
And millions more behind them.
也许 嗯 它们只是天文数字
And sure, m-may... Yeah, maybe they were just math.
却好像在翩翩起舞
But they also danced.
我知道 因为那一瞬我看见了
I know 'cause I saw one of them.
我那时想 宇宙广阔无限
And I remember thinking, the universe is large
宇宙包罗万象
and, and it contains multitudes,
也包含了我
but it-it also contains me.
而在那一刻 我真觉得自己很精彩
And in this moment...I am wonderful.
我理应拥有这份精彩
And I have a right to be wonderful.
啊
Oh!
干嘛为这事撒谎 小傻瓜
Why lie about that, silly?
你真是个奇妙的存在 亲爱的
You're a strange wonder, my dear.
他没再多说 因为那道疤另有深意
He doesn't offer more because the scar was important for another reason.
是他讲不完的故事的一环
It was part of a story he couldn't tell,
其中有他长大的那幢维多利亚老宅
even though there was now an apartment building on the site of the Victorian house
尽管早拆了盖楼了
where he had done most of his growing up.
那幢闹鬼的维多利亚老宅
The haunted Victorian house.
不知道
No reason.
就是心血来潮吧
Funny thinking, I guess.
这疤意义非凡 他也尽力讲得加料
The scar meant more, so he had made it more.
可讲得总没有它真正的意义深
He just couldn't make it as much more as it really was.
讲得还有点糊涂
That made little sense.
但随着脑癌细胞的疯狂进攻
But as the glioblastoma continued its blitzkrieg,
他那快散架的大脑最多也只能讲到这样
it was the best his disintegrating mind could manage.
查克的爷爷 他的阿爷
Chuck's grandpa, his Zaydee,
在那场秋季舞会五年后 因心脏病发作去世
died of a heart attack five years after the Fall Fling dance.
事发时查克读高二
Chuck was a junior in high school
是乐队主唱
singing in a band and
正在台上像摇滚巨星一样跳得带劲儿
dancing like Jagger during the instrumental breaks.
他自己都安排妥当了
He made all the arrangements himself.
几周前
Came in a few weeks ago
还特地来馆里再确认一遍
just to make sure everything was to the letter,
我还纳闷呢
which I thought was strange.
很少有人这么上心
Not many people bother to do that.
大多数人只来一趟定好流程
Most people, they come here once to set it all up.
办好手续就不再来了
They aren't anxious to come back again.
再见到那人 都是穿着体面衣服躺那儿 懂吧
Next time I see 'em, they're in their Sunday best, if you get me.
他人特好 也是我多年的好友
He was a great man and a good friend.
他为我们做账整整二十三年了
He's been doing our books for 23 years
账做得稳 多次税务检查都帮我们顺利过关
and saved our skin more than once when the tax man was coming.
要现在给你结账吗？
So, do I owe you any money?
一分都不用
Not a penny.
他那次来就把钱全给结清了
He took care of that too. Settled his tab that same visit.
听我说
You know...
最离奇的是
the strangest thing.
这事儿很怪 可别觉得我扯
And this will sound strange, so bear with me.
说来话长
See,
年轻时我曾想当电视上天气预报员
I, uh, dreamed of being a television weatherman in my salad days
也许能成全国台的
with maybe one of the networks.
最终没成
Wasn't in the cards for me.
倒是去地方台待过一个夏天
But I did spend a summer at WKNB.
在那儿 有个同事号称能
Well, there was a guy at KNB who they said
不用雷达就能提前两周感知风暴
could feel a storm coming two solid weeks away without the radar.
有第六感
Had a sixth sense.
简直了
Damnedest thing I ever saw.
他会露出一种神情
Uh, used to make this face,
当别人说要出远门
this face when people talked about their travel plans,
然后他洞察出什么后
if he knew something they didn't.
那神情不笑不乐
Not... not a smile, per se. No joy in it.
就一脸 我全知道的样子
Just a... knowing.
我管那叫 预报员天眼
"Weatherman Stare," I called it.
我可没那本事
And I didn't have it, not me.
所以我在这行 而不是那行
So, I'm here, not there.
你爷爷来时也带着同样的神情
Your granddad had that same face when he was in here.
像是 他早料到要下雨
Like... he knew it was gonna rain.
而我只是个卖他伞的人
And I was just a guy selling him an umbrella.
那就是预报员天眼
Weatherman Stare.
我敢打包票
I'm sure of it.
太离谱了
The strangest thing.
爷爷阿尔比把一切家当都留给了他
Albie left him everything.
这足够支付他的大学学费
More than enough to pay for his college education.
再后来 他把那幢维多利亚老宅卖了
And later on, the sale of the Victorian
用这笔钱买了
paid for the house he and Ginny moved into
和他妻子珍妮度蜜月后住的新家
after their honeymoon in the Catskills.
他铁了心不去奥马哈和外公外婆一起住
He flatly refused to move to Omaha to live with his mother's parents.
-听着 我真的很爱你们... -他这样说
-Look, I love you guys... -He said.
...但我在这里长大的 也想在这待到上大学
...but this is where I grew up and want to stay till college.
我都17了 不是小孩子了
I'm 17. I'm not a baby.
于是 早已退休的老两口 住进那幢维多利亚老宅
So, they, both long retired, came to him and stayed in the Victorian
陪查克二十多个月
for the 20-odd months before Chuck went off
直到他去伊利诺伊大学
to the University of Illinois.
可他们没赶上参加葬礼
They weren't able to be there for the funeral, however.
葬礼办得很快 正如阿尔比所愿
It happened fast, as Albie had wanted,
他外公外婆在奥马哈还有一些事要收尾
and his mom's folks had loose ends to tie up in Omaha.
说实话 查克并不怎么想他们
Chuck didn't really miss them, if he was honest.
他跟他阿爷一样 最讨厌瞎折腾 也受不了人多
His Zaydee hated a fuss almost as much as he hated a crowd.
他们来的前一天
A day before they were scheduled to arrive,
查克才拆开
Chuck finally opened the envelope
放玄关桌上的那大信封
that had been sitting on the table in the front hall.
信封是来自山姆·雅伯勒
It was from Sam Yarborough,
亚伯勒殡仪馆的老板兼首席殡葬师
owner and chief undertaker at Yarborough Funeral Home,
里面装着阿尔比·克兰兹的个人物品
and inside were Albie Krantz's personal effects.
在这屋里 查克爷爷见过杰弗里家那男孩
In this room, Chuck's grandpa had seen the Jefferies boy,
被车撞得血肉模糊
body broken by the car.
他见过亨利·彼得森吊在天花板上
He'd seen Henry Peterson hanging from the ceiling.
他还见过他妻子躺在地上断了气
He'd seen his own wife lying dead.
查克想
And likely, Chuck supposed,
也许就在那晚他偷钥匙的时候
perhaps the night Chuck had stolen his keys,
阿尔比还看见自己摔倒在地
Albie had even seen himself crumpled to the floor,
死死抓着胳膊
still clutching his upper arm.
“这就是等待”他说
"It's the waiting," he'd said.
“这是最难熬的”
"That's the hard part."
现在轮到查克自己的煎熬了
Now Chuck's own waiting would begin.
他到底要等多久？
How long would that wait be?
病床上那个人到底多少岁？
Exactly how old was the man in the hospital bed?
看不见的监护仪发出最后一声“哔”
There was a final bip from the unseen monitor
然后也随之消失
and then that was gone too.
他不像电影里那样慢慢淡去
The man did not fade, as ghostly apparitions did in the movies.
就直接不见了
He was just gone.
仿佛他从未出现过
Insisting he had never been there in the first place.
-那不可能... -查克想
-He wasn't... -Chuck thinks.
...我偏不信
...and I will insist he wasn't.
我会痛痛快快地活 直到最后一刻
And I will live my life until my life runs out.
我很精彩
I am wonderful.
我配得上这份精彩
I deserve to be wonderful.
我包罗万象
And I contain multitudes.
导演及影片编剧
迈克·弗拉纳根
原著短篇小说
史蒂芬·金
查克的一生
蒙太奇字幕组 原创翻译 转载须遵循CC BY-NC-SA 4.0协议
翻译：小P  后期：novaeye & 小P
字幕组纳新TG：MontageSubs
谨以缅怀
斯科特·沃普勒
本故事纯属虚构 如有雷同纯属巧合